in the last chapter you and I started to
step through the internal workings of a
transformer this is one of the key
pieces of Technology inside large
language models and a lot of other tools
in the Modern Wave of AI it first hit
the scene in a now famous 2017 paper
called attention is all you need and in
this chapter you and I will dig into
what this attention mechanism is
visualizing how it processes
data as a quick recap here's the
important context I want you to have in
mind the goal of the model that you and
I are studying is to take in a piece of
text and predict what word comes next
the input text is broken up into little
pieces that we call tokens and these are
very often words or pieces of words but
just to make the examples in this video
easier for you and me to think about
let's simplify by pretending that tokens
are always just words the first step in
a Transformer is to associate each token
with a high dimensional Vector what we
call its embedding now the most
important idea I want you to have in
mind is how directions in this
high-dimensional space of all possible
embeddings can correspond with semantic
meaning in the last chapter we saw an
example for how Direction can correspond
to gender in the sense that adding a
certain step in this space can take you
from the embedding of a masculine noun
to the embedding of the corresponding
feminine noun that's just one example
you could imagine how many other
directions in this high-dimensional
space could correspond to numerous other
aspects of a word's
meaning the aim of a transformer is to
progressively adjust these embeddings so
that they don't merely encode an
individual word but instead they bake in
some much much richer contextual meaning
I should say up front that a lot of
people find the attention mechanism this
key piece in a Transformer very
confusing so don't worry if it takes
some time for things to sink in I think
that before we dive into the
computational details and all the Matrix
multiplications it's worth thinking
about a couple examples for the kind of
behavior that we want attention to
enable consider the phrases American
true mole one mole of carbon dioxide and
take a biopsy of the mole you and I know
that the word mole has different
meanings in each one of these based on
the context but after the first step of
a transformer the one that breaks up the
text and Associates each token with a
vector the vector that's associated with
mole would be the same in all three of
these cases because this initial token
embedding is effectively a lookup table
with no reference to the context it's
only in the next step of the Transformer
that the surrounding embeddings have the
chance to pass information into this one
the picture you might have in mind is
that there are multiple distinct
directions in this embedding space
encoding the multiple distinct meanings
of the word mole and that a well-trained
attention block calculates what you need
to add to the generic embedding to move
it to one of these more specific
directions as a function of the
context to take another example consider
the embedding of the word tower this is
presumably some very generic
non-specific Direction in the space
associated with lots of other large tall
nouns if this word was immediately
preceded by Eiffel you could imagine
wanting the mechanism to update this
Vector so that it points in a direction
that more specifically encodes the
Eiffel Tower maybe correlated with
vectors associated with Paris and France
and things made of steel if it was also
preceded by the word miniature then the
vector should be updated even further so
that it no longer correlates with large
tall
things more generally than just refining
the meaning of a word the attention
block allows the model to move
information encoded in one embedding to
that of another potentially ones that
are quite far away and potentially with
information that's much richer than just
a single word what we saw in the last
chapter was how after all of the vectors
flow through the network including many
different attention blocks the
computation that you perform to produce
a prediction of the next token is
entirely a function of the last Vector
in the sequence so imagine for example
that the text you input is most of an
entire mystery novel all the way up to a
point near the end which reads therefore
the murderer was if the model's going to
accurately predict the next word that
final Vector in the sequence which began
its life simply embedding the word was
will have to have been updated by all of
the attention blocks to represent much
much more than any individual word
somehow encoding all of the information
from the full context window that's
relevant to predicting the next
word to step through the computations
though let's take a much simpler example
imagine that the input includes the
phrase a fluffy blue creature roamed The
Verdant forest and for the moment
suppose that the only type of update
that we care about is having the
adjectives adjust the meanings of their
corresponding nouns what I'm about to
describe is what we would call a single
head of attention and later we will see
how the attention block consists of many
different heads run in parallel again
the initial embedding for each word is
some high-dimensional vector that only
encodes the meaning of that particular
word with no context actually that's not
quite true they also encode the position
of the word there's a lot more to say
about the specific way that positions
are encoded but right now all you need
to know is that the entries of this
Vector are enough to tell you both what
the word is and where it exists in the
context let's go ahead and denote these
embeddings with the letter E the goal is
to have a series of computations produce
a new refined set of embeddings where
for example those corresponding to the
nouns have ingested the meaning from
their corresponding adjectives and
playing the Deep learning game we want
most of the computations involved to
look like Matrix Vector products where
the matrices are full of tunable weights
things that the model will learn Based
on data to be clear I'm making up this
example of adjectives updating nouns
just to illustrate the type of behavior
that you could imagine an intention head
doing as with so much deep learning the
true behavior is much harder to parse
because it's based on tweaking and
tuning a huge number of parameters to
minimize some cost function it's just
that as we step through all of the
different matrices filled with
parameters that are involved in this
process I think it's really helpful to
have an imagined example of something
that it could be doing to help keep it
all more concrete for the first step of
this process you might imagine each noun
like creature asking the question hey
are there any adjectives sitting in
front of me and for the words fluffy and
blue to each be able to answer yeah I'm
an adjective and I'm in that
position that question is somehow
encoded as yet another Vector another
list of numbers which we call the query
for this word this query Vector though
has a much smaller Dimension than the
embedding Vector say
128 Computing this query looks like
taking a certain Matrix which I'll label
WQ and multiplying it by the
embedding compressing things a bit let's
write that query Vector as q and then
anytime you see me put a matrix next to
an arrow like this one it's meant to
represent that multiplying this matrix
by the vector at the Arrow's start gives
you the vector at the Arrow's
end in this case you multiply this
matrix by all of the embeddings in the
context producing one query Vector for
each token the entries of this Matrix
are parameters of the model which means
the true behavior is learned from data
and in practice what this Matrix does in
a particular attention head is
challenging to parse but for our sake
imagining an example that we might hope
that it would learn we'll suppose that
this query Matrix Maps the embed Bings
of nouns to certain directions in this
smaller query space that somehow encodes
the notion of looking for adjectives in
preceding positions as to what it does
to other embeddings who knows maybe it
simultaneously tries to accomplish some
other goal with those right now we're
laser focused on the nouns at the same
time associated with this is a second
Matrix called the key Matrix which you
also multiply by every one of the
embeddings this produces a second
sequence of vectors that we call the
keys consider seally you want to think
of the keys as potentially answering the
queries this key Matrix is also full of
tunable parameters and just like the
query Matrix It Maps the embedding
vectors to that same smaller dimensional
space you think of the keys as matching
the queries whenever they closely align
with each other in our example you would
imagine that the key Matrix Maps the
adjectives like fluffy and blue to
vectors that are closely aligned with
the query produced by the word creature
to measure how well each key matches
each query you compute a DOT product
between each possible key query pair I
like to visualize a grid full of a bunch
of dots where the bigger dots correspond
to the larger dot products the places
where the keys and queries align for our
adjective noun example that would look a
little more like this where if the keys
produced by fluffy and blue really do
align closely with the query produced by
creature then the dot products in these
two spots would be some large positive
numbers in the link dingo machine
learning people would say that this
means the embeddings of fluffy and blue
attend to the embedding of creature by
contrast to the dot product between the
key for some other word like the and the
query for creature would be some small
or negative value that reflects that
these are unrelated to each
other so we have this grid of values
that can be any real number from
negative Infinity to Infinity giving us
a score for how relevant each word is to
updating the meaning of every other word
the way we're about to use these scores
is to take a certain weighted Sum along
each column weighted by the relevance so
instead of having values range from
negative Infinity to Infinity what we
want is for the numbers in these columns
to be between 0 and 1 and for each
column to add up to one as if they were
a probability
distribution if you're coming in from
the last chapter you know what we need
to do then we compute a soft Max along
each one of these columns to normalize
the values
in our picture after you apply softmax
to all of the columns we'll fill in the
grid with these normalized values at
this point you're safe to think about
each column as giving weights according
to how relevant the word on the left is
to the corresponding value at the top we
call this grid an attention pattern now
if you look at the original Transformer
paper there's a really compact way that
they write this all down here the
variables q and K represent the full
arrays of query and key vector vectors
respectively those little vectors you
get by multiplying the embeddings by the
query and the key matrices this
expression up in the numerator is a
really compact way to represent the grid
of all possible dot products between
Pairs of keys and queries a small
technical detail that I didn't mention
is that for numerical stability it
happens to be helpful to divide all of
these values by the square root of the
dimension in that key query space then
this soft Max that's wrapped around the
full expression is meant to be
understood to apply column by column as
to that V term we'll talk about it in
just a second before that there's one
other technical detail that so far I
have skipped during the training process
when you run this model on a given text
example and all of the weights are
slightly adjusted and tuned to either
reward or punish it based on how high a
probability it assigns to the true next
word in the passage it turns out to make
the whole training process a lot more
efficient if you simultaneously have it
predict every possible next token
following each initial subsequence of
tokens in this passage for example with
the phrase that we've been focusing on
it might also be predicting what words
follow creature and what words follow
the this is really nice because it means
what would otherwise be a single
training example effectively acts as
many for the purposes of our attention
pattern it means that you never want to
allow later words to influence earlier
words since otherwise they could kind of
give away the answer for what comes next
what this means is that we want all of
these spots here the ones ones
representing later tokens influencing
earlier ones to somehow be forced to be
zero the simplest thing you might think
to do is to set them equal to zero but
if you did that the columns wouldn't add
up to one anymore they wouldn't be
normalized so instead a common way to do
this is that before applying softmax you
set all of those entries to be negative
Infinity if you do that then after
applying soft Max all of those get
turned into zero but the columns stay
normalized this process is called
masking there are versions of attention
where you don't apply it but in our GPT
example even though this is more
relevant during the training phase than
it would be say running it as a chatbot
or something like that you do always
apply this masking to prevent later
tokens from influencing earlier ones
another fact that's worth reflecting on
about this attention pattern is how its
size is equal to the square of the
context size so this is why context size
can be a really huge bottleneck for
large language models and scaling it up
is non-trivial As you might imagine
motivated by a desire for bigger and
bigger context Windows recent years have
seen some variations to the attention
mechanism aimed at making context more
scalable but right here you and I are
staying focused on the
basics okay great Computing this pattern
lets the model deduce which words are
relevant to which other words now you
need to actually update the embeddings
allowing words to pass information to
whichever other words they're relevant
to for example you want the embedding of
fluffy to somehow cause a change to
creature that moves it to a different
part of this 12,000 dimensional
embedding space that more specifically
encodes a fluffy creature what I'm going
to do here is first show you the most
straightforward way that you could do
this though there's a slight way that
this gets modified in the context of
multi-headed attention this most
straightforward way would be to use a
third Matrix what we call the value
Matrix which you multiply by the
embedding of that first word for example
fluffy the result of this is what you
would call a value vector and this is
something that you add to the embedding
of the SE word in this case something
you add to the embedding of creature so
this value Vector lives in the same very
high dimensional space as the embeddings
when you multiply this value matrix by
the embedding of a word you might think
of it as saying if this word is relevant
to adjusting the meaning of something
else what exactly should be added to the
embedding of that something else in
order to reflect this looking back in
our diagram let's set aside all of the
keys and the queries since after you
compute the attention pattern you're
done with those then you're going to
take this value Matrix and multiply it
by every one of those embeddings to
produce a sequence of value vectors you
might think of these value vectors as
being kind of associated with the
corresponding
keys for each column in this diagram you
multiply each of the value vectors by
the corresponding weight in that column
for example here under the embedding of
creature you would be adding large
proportions of the value vectors for
fluffy and blue while all of the other
value vectors get zero out or at least
nearly zero out and then finally the way
to actually update the embedding
associated with this column previously
encoding some context-free meaning of
creature you add together all of these
rescaled values in the column producing
a change that you want to add that all
label Delta e and then you add that to
the original embedding hopefully what
results is a more refined Vector
encoding the more contextually Rich
meaning like that of a fluffy blue
creature and of course you don't just do
this to one embedding you apply the same
weighted sum across all of the columns
in this picture producing a sequence of
changes adding all of those changes to
the corresponding embeddings produces a
full sequence of more refined embeddings
popping out of the attention
block zooming out this whole process is
what you would describe as a single head
of attention as I've described things so
far this process is parameterized by
three distinct matrices all filled with
tunable parameters the key the query and
the value I want to take a moment to
continue what we started in the last
chapter with the scorekeeping where we
count up the total number of model
parameters using the numbers from
gpt3 these key and query matrices each
have 12,288 columns matching the
embedding Dimension and 128 rows
matching the dimension of that smaller
key query space this gives us an
additional 1.5 million or so parameters
for each one if you look at that value
matrix by contrast the way I've
described things so far would suggest
that it's a square Matrix that has
12,288 columns and 12,288 rows since
both its inputs and its outputs live in
this very large embedding space if true
that would mean about 150 million added
parameters and to be clear you could do
that you could devote orders of
magnitude more parameters to the value
map than to the key in query but in
practice it is much more efficient If
instead you make it so that the number
of parameters devoted to this value map
is the same as the number devoted to the
key in the query this is especially
relevant in the setting of running
multiple attention heads in parallel the
way this looks is that the value map is
factored as a product of two smaller
matrices conceptually I would still
encourage you to think about the overall
linear map one with inputs and outputs
both in this larger embedding space for
example taking the embedding of blue to
this bless direction that you would add
to nouns it's just that it's broken up
into two separate steps the first Matrix
on the right here has a smaller number
of rows typically the same size as the
key query space what this means is you
can think of it as mapping the large
embedding vectors down to a much smaller
space this is not the conventional
naming but I'm going to call this the
value down Matrix the second Matrix maps
from the smaller space back up to the
embedding space producing the vectors
that you use to make the actual updates
I'm going to call this one the value up
Matrix which again is not conventional
the way that you would see this written
in most papers looks a little different
I'll talk about it in a minute in my
opinion it tends to make things a little
more conceptually confusing to throw in
linear algebra jargon here what we're
basically doing is constraining the
overall value map to be a low rank
transformation turning back to the
parameter count all four of these
matrices have the same size and adding
them all up we get about 6.3 million
parameters for one attention
head as a quick side note to be a little
more accurate everything described so
far is what people would call a self
attention head to distinguish it from a
very that comes up in other models
that's called cross attention this isn't
relevant to our GPT example but if
you're curious cross attention involves
models that process two distinct types
of data like text in one language and
text in another language that's part of
an ongoing generation of a translation
or maybe audio input of speech and an
ongoing
transcription a cross attention head
looks almost identical the only
difference is that the key and query
Maps act on different data sets in a
model doing translation for example the
keys might come from one language while
the queries come from another and the
attention pattern could describe which
words from one language correspond to
which words in another and in this
setting there would typically be no
masking since there's not really any
notion of later tokens affecting earlier
ones staying focused on self attention
though if you understood everything so
far and if you were to stop here you
would come away with the essence of what
attention really is all that's really
left to us is to lay out the sense sense
in which you do this many many different
times in our Central example we focused
on adjectives updating nouns but of
course there are lots of different ways
that context can influence the meaning
of a word if the words they crashed thee
preceded the word car it has
implications for the shape and the
structure of that car and a lot of
associations might be less grammatical
if the word wizard is anywhere in the
same passage as Harry it suggests that
this might be referring to Harry Potter
whereas if instead the words Queen
Sussex and William were in that passage
then perhaps the embedding of Harry
should instead be updated to refer to
the prince for every different type of
contextual updating that you might
imagine the parameters of these key
inquery matrices would be different to
capture the different attention patterns
and the parameters of our value map
would be different based on what should
be added to the embeddings and again in
practice the true behavior of these Maps
is much more difficult to interpret
where the weights are set to do whatever
the model needs them to do to best
accomplish its goal of predicting the
next
token as I said before everything we
described as a single head of attention
and a full attention block inside a
Transformer consists of what's called
multi-headed attention where you run a
lot of these operations in parallel each
with its own distinct key query and
value
maps gpt3 for example uses 96 attention
heads inside each block considering that
each one is already a bit confusing it's
certainly a lot to hold in your head
just to spell it all out very explicitly
this means you have 96 distinct key and
query matrices producing 96 distinct
attention patterns then each head has
its own distinct value matrices used to
produce 96 sequences of value vectors
these are all added together using the
corresponding attention patterns as
weights what this means is that for each
position in the context each token every
one of these heads produces a proposed
change to be added to the embedding in
that position so what you do is you sum
together all of those proposed changes
one for each head and you add the result
to the original embedding of that
position this entire sum here would be
one slice of what's outputed from this
multi-headed attention block a single
one of those refined embeddings that
pops out the other end of it again this
is a lot to think about so don't worry
at all if it takes some time to sink in
the overall idea is that by running many
distinct heads in parallel you're giving
the model the capacity to learn many
distinct ways that context changes
meaning pulling up our running tally for
parameter count with 96 heads each
including its own variation of these
four matrices each block of multi-headed
detention ends up with around 600
million
parameters there's one added slightly
annoying thing that I should really
mention for any of you who go on to read
more about Transformers you remember how
I said that the value map is factored
out into these two distinct matrices
which I labeled as the value down and
the value up matrices the way that I
framed things would suggest that you see
this pair of matrices inside each
attention head and you could absolutely
implement it this way that would be a
valid design but the way that you see
this written in papers and the way that
it's implemented in practice looks a
little different all of these value up
matrices for each head appear stapled
together in one giant Matrix that we
call the output Matrix associated with
the entire multi-headed attention block
and when you see people refer to the
value Matrix for a given attention head
they're typically only referring to this
first step the one that I was labeling
as the value down projection into the
smaller space for the Curious among you
I've left an on-screen note about it
it's one of those details that runs the
risk of distracting from the main
conceptual points but I do want to call
it out just so that you know if you read
about this in other sources setting
aside all the technical nuances in the
preview from the last chapter we saw how
data flowing through a Transformer
doesn't just flow through a single
attention block for one thing it also
goes through these other operations
called multi-layer perceptrons we'll
talk more about those in the next
chapter and then it repeatedly goes
through many many copies of both of
these operations what this means is that
after a given word embies some of its
context there are many more chances for
this more nuanced embedding to be
influenced by its more nuanced
surroundings the further down the
network you go with each embedding
taking in more and more meaning from all
the other embeddings which themselves
are getting more and more new nuanced
the hope is that there's the capacity to
encode higher level and more abstract
ideas about a given input Beyond just
descriptors and grammatical structure
things like sentiment and tone and
whether it's a poem and what underlying
scientific truths are relevant to the
piece and things like
that turning back one more time to our
scorekeeping gpt3 includes 96 distinct
layers so the total number of key query
and value parameters is multiplied by
another 96 which brings the total sum to
just under 58 billion distinct
parameters devoted to all of the
attention heads that is a lot to be sure
but it's only about a third of the 175
billion that are in the network in total
so even though attention gets all of the
attention the majority of parameters
come from the blocks sitting in between
these steps in the next chapter you and
I will talk more about those other
blocks and also a lot more about the
training process a big part of the story
for the success of the attention
mechanism is not so much any specific
kind of behavior that it enables but the
fact that it's extremely parallelizable
meaning that you can run a huge number
of computations in a short time using
gpus given that one of the big lessons
about deep learning in the last decade
or two has been that scale alone seems
to give huge qualitative improvements in
model performance there's a huge
advantage to parallelizable
architectures that let you do this if
you want to learn more about this stuff
I've left lots of links in the
description in particular anything
produced by Andre carpy or Chris Ola
tend to be pure gold in this video I
wanted to just jump into attention in
its current form but if you're curious
about more of the history for how we got
here and how you might reinvent this
idea for yourself my friend VC just put
up a couple videos giving a lot more of
that motivation also Brit Cruz from the
channel the art of the problem has a
really nice video about the history of
large language models